奋进号 这里是休斯敦 主发动机关机正常 欢迎来到太空
Endeavor, Houston, we see a nominal MECO, welcome to space.
再入段是航天飞行中最惊心动魄的阶段
Reentry is a daunting part of space flight,
尤其乘坐一艘需要无动力滑行降落在跑道上的航天器的时候
especially when you're in a large spacecraft that has to land on a runway, as a glider.
欢迎观看 航天飞机再入制导与控制介绍
This, is Space Shuttle reentry Guidance and control.
我们的目标是让近地轨道上速度超过每秒7公里的航天飞机轨道器
Our objective is to get the Space Shuttle Orbiter from low earth orbit, traveling at approximately 7 km/s,
最终完全停在肯尼迪航天中心的航天飞机着陆场
to a complete stop on a runway, in this case, the Shuttle landing facility at the Kennedy Space Center.
再入段始于轨道器的离轨点火
To begin reentry, the Orbiter will conduct a deorbit burn,
让轨道器的轨迹切入地球大气层
bringing a trajectory on a path to intersect the atmosphere.
重点是控制轨道器产生多大的气动阻力
Controlling how much aerodynamic drag the Orbiter generates is essential,
保证我们以正确速率降低高度与速度来接近跑道
ensuring that we lose altitude and velocity at the correct rate to reach the runway.
阻力有多重要? 再入段制导系统就是围绕阻力运行的
In fact, this is so important, the reentry guidance system thinks in terms of drag,
或者更专业的名词 运行于"速度-阻力加速度状态空间"
or if you prefer more technical terms, it operates in a velocity-drag state space.
如图为速度-阻力加速度图表 描述了航天飞机再入制导的大部分内容
This is a drag versus velocity graph, and it's a major part of Shuttle reentry guidance.
绿线表示航天飞机的通常再入数据
This green line shows a generic Shuttle reentry profile,
曲线的形状受制于上下两部分边界
and the shape of this line is influenced by some upper and lower boundaries.
蓝色为过冲边界 此处阻力太小
In blue, we have the overshoot boundary, generating two little drag.
也叫"软边界"
This is known as a "soft boundary",
因为阻力来到这个区域不会摧毁轨道器 但也好不到哪去
because crossing this boundary won't destroy the Orbiter, but it will really ruin your day.
航天器会有重新弹回太空的风险 减小再次再入成功着陆的概率
You'll potentially skip back out of the atmosphere with less than great prospects of a secondary entry attempt.
undershoot有"未达跑道着陆"的意思 就是阻力太大了
上方的红色区域为阻力过大边界
Up above in red, we've got the undershoot boundary, generating too much drag.
此区域为硬边界
This is a hard boundary,
意味着轨道器在此可能超过结构与热量限制而发生损伤
because crossing this boundary will cause damage to the Orbiter, by exceeding structural and thermal limits.
在上下边界中间剩下的 就是"再入飞行走廊"了
Between these upper and lower boundaries, we are left with the flight corridor,
这条蜿蜒的"走廊"要求我们在再入段中随时调整阻力
and it leaves us with a little bit of wiggle room to adjust our drag profile throughout the reentry
保证我们相对跑道有一个正确的飞行距离
to ensure that we can fly the correct distance to the runway.
我刚刚说这是"通常数据" 因为航天飞机每次飞行的数据是不同的
I said this is a generic profile, and that's because every Space Shuttle flight is different,
取决于返回时载荷质量与轨道倾角等
depending on things such as payload return mass and orbital inclination.
每次飞行会定制当次的走廊边界与阻力数据
The boundaries and nominal drag profile will be tailored for each flight.
现在我们知道 控制阻力是非常非常重要的
We've now established that controlling drag is very, very important.
那么问题来了: 如何控制阻力?
But that raises the question: how do we control drag?
首先为大家介绍"攻角"
First, let's start with something called "angle of attack".
攻角是气流与机翼(翼弦)的夹角
Angle of attack is the angle between air flow and a wing.
当然 本例中 气流方向与速度方向刚好相反
And of course, in this instance, that airflow is just opposite to our velocity.
因此在本例中 我们可以简单认为 攻角就是机翼与速度方向的夹角
So a simplification we can make in some cases such as this
is to say that angle of attack is the angle between the wing and our velocity.
画面中 轨道器的飞行攻角为40度
Right now, you can see the Orbiter flying at an angle of attack of 40 degrees.
该视角下 我们能注意到阻力是由迎面而来的气流推动轨道器产生的
From this perspective, we can see drag is generated by the oncoming airflow pushing on the Orbiter.
攻角增大时
When the angle of attack is increased,
会有更大的参考面积迎接气流
a larger forward cross sectional area is presented towards the oncoming airflow.
导致轨道器的阻力增加
And so the Orbiter experiences more drag.
相反 攻角降低时 迎接气流的参考面积降低
When the angle of attack is decreased, less cross sectional area is presented to the air flow,
阻力也随之降低
and so drag decreases.
同时 攻角不但会影响阻力 还会影响升力
However, angle of attack doesn't just influence drag, it also influences lift.
攻角(从零开始)增加时 升力和阻力都会增加
As our angle of attack increases, our lift and drag both increase.
但到了某一刻  阻力会继续增加 升力会转而减小
While our drag will keep increasing, lift will only increase to a point, then start to decrease.
倒也好理解 毕竟完全垂直的机翼不可能产生升力
This does make sense, right? You wouldn't expect a wing perpendicular to airflow like this to generate any lift,
但阻力却是相当大的
but you would expect it to generate a lot of drag.
这段原视频内容有大量名词定义错误
看我中文翻译大概知道意思即可
我们可以把升力与阻力组合为"升阻比"
We can combine lift and drag together into a lift to drag ratio,
并将升阻比与攻角的关系画成曲线
and then compare this to angle of attack.
"lift curve"应当是升力系数与攻角的曲线
如图 是升阻比与攻角的曲线 即"升阻比曲线"
And so here we have a lift to drag ratio versus angle of attack curve, referred to as a lift curve.
临界攻角(critical angle of attack)
是升力曲线顶点对应的攻角
而不是升阻比曲线顶点对应的攻角
以升阻比曲线的顶点对应的攻角飞行时 飞机的升阻比最大
At the top of the lift curve, we find the critical angle of attack, where we have the highest lift to drag ratio,
攻角小于此时 升阻比正相关于攻角
flying at a lower angle of attack than this, as known as flying on the front side of the lift curve.
而航天飞机在再入段 轨道器会以大于此攻角的姿态飞行
However, during reentry, the Orbiter flies on the back side of the lift curve,
此时升阻比负相关于攻角
having an angle of attack higher than the critical angle.
我们现在学会用攻角调节轨道器收到的阻力了
We've seen that we can use angle of attack to control how much drag the Orbiter experiences,
但这只能用于微调
but this is only fine control.
在再入段的早期
In the early reentry phases,
气动热量约束会限制轨道器保持40度左右的攻角
aerothermal constraints limit us to stay pretty close to 40 degrees angle of attack.
攻角能改变的量只有正负3度左右 称为攻角调节
The small changes that we can make to our angle of attack
of about plus or minus 3 degrees are called alpha modulation.
但攻角调节并不能满足刚刚飞行走廊中的阻力数据
But alpha modulation alone is insufficient for achieving the drag profile that we saw earlier.
我们需要另一种方式来控制阻力 一种间接的方式
We need another method of controlling our drag, and this is an indirect one.
倾侧角
Bank angle.
倾侧角是相对速度矢量的旋转度数
Bank angle is the angle of rotation about the axis of the velocity vector.
如果我们从前方沿着速度矢量看轨道器 可以看到0度的倾侧角
If we look at the Orbiter from the front, along the velocity vector, we can see a bank angle of zero degrees.
然后倾侧角增加到20度
Now let's increase the bank angle to 20 degrees,
然后增加到60度
and increase it again to 60.
这就是倾侧角
That's bank angle.
我们再换个视角 了解另一个重要概念
Let's take a different viewpoint now to note something very important.
倾侧角和攻角是两个互相独立的量
Bank angle and angle of attack are independent of one another.
我可以保持攻角不变 只调整轨道器的倾侧角 也可以反过来
I can change the Shuttle's bank angle without changing the angle of attack, and vice versa.
我可以只改变攻角 而保持倾侧角不变
I can change the angle of attack without changing the bank angle.
那倾侧角是如何影响阻力的?
Now, how does bank angle influence our drag
看起来 改变倾侧角并不会像改变攻角那样影响气流的参考面积
when it clearly doesn't change the frontal area presented to airflow like angle of attacked it?
增加倾侧角作用是让升力矢量从向上改为指向两侧
The effect of increasing our bank angle is to point less of our lift upwards by pointing at sideways.
零倾侧角时 升力是垂直向上的
With a zero degree bank angle, all of our lift is pointing straight up.
但比如倾侧角45度时 一半的升力向上 一半的升力向一侧
But with, say, a 45 degree bank angle, half of our lift is pointed up and half is pointing sideways.
我们可以通过控制升力的垂直分量来控制轨道器的下降率
By controlling how much vertical lift is exerted, we can influence the Orbiter's descent rate.
控制了下降率 就能控制阻力
By influencing descent rate, we can influence drag.
因为阻力与速度的平方正相关
This is because drag is proportional to the square of velocity,
而下降率就是速度的一部分
and descent rate is a component of our velocity.
所以 这个流程是这样的:
Hence this chain of effects:
增加倾侧角 减少垂直方向升力
Increase bank angle, decreases vertical lift,
增加下降率 增加速度 增加阻力
which increases descent rate, adding to a velocity, hence adding to a drag,
反过来就是:
And vice versa:
减小倾侧角 增加垂直方向升力
Decreased bank angle, increases vertical lift,
降低下降率 减小速度 减小阻力
decreasing descent rate, decreasing velocity and decreasing drag.
至此 我们有了两种控制阻力的方法:
There we have our two methods of controlling our drag:
直接方式 调整攻角 间接方式 调整倾侧角
directly with angle of attack and indirectly with bank angle.
轨道器会同时使用两种方式来达到阻力值的需求
And we use these two methods simultaneously to achieve the desire drag profile.
那么新问题来了:
This leads us to another question:
如何控制倾侧角和攻角?
how do we control our bank angle and angle of attack?
再入段初始时期 几乎没有大气
At the start of reentry, there's no atmosphere around us,
因此体襟翼 升降副翼和方向舵等气动控制面并没有什么作用
so our aerodynamic control surfaces consisting of the body flap, elevons and rudder aren't very useful,
此时轨道器使用反作用控制系统(RCS)推进器进行姿态调整
so we'll use the reaction control system thrusters.
这些小推进器分布在轨道器四周
These are small thrusters located at various positions around the Orbiter,
之前在轨时可提供精确机动控制
used to provide precise maneuvering control while we were in orbit.
但RCS也不会用太久
However, we don't have to rely on the reaction control system for too long.
滚转推进器
俯仰推进器
偏航推进器
方向舵
升降舵
副翼
减速板
体襟翼
当我们进入大气层 动压迅速增加
As we into the atmosphere, dynamic pressure starts to build up fairly quickly,
姿态就可以从RCS慢慢过渡到气动面控制了
allowing us to switch from reaction control to aerodynamic control.
有趣的是 控制偏航的方向舵是最后接管RCS的
Interestingly, the yaw access with the rudder
is the last control access to transition from reaction to aerodynamic control,
原因也很有意思
and the reason is pretty neat.
因为在40度的高攻角姿态下
It's because of a high 40 degree angle of attack,
方向舵始终处在轨道器的尾流内
meaning the rudder is in the Orbiter's aerodynamic wake.
方向舵没有足够动压来进行姿态控制
This simply not enough dynamic pressure back there for the rudder to be effective
直到再入段末期 轨道器仰角降低 方向舵才能用
until the Orbiter starts to pitch its nose down late into the reentry.
既然聊到了空气动力学
While we're on the topic of aerodynamics,
大家可能会奇怪为什么轨道器机翼前部有这样窄窄的一条三角形部分
you may have wondered why the Orbiter's wings have these Sticky Outty Front Bits.
它们是"前缘根部延伸" 是轨道器双三角翼的一部分
These are Leading Edge Root Extensions, and they form part of the Orbiter's double delta wing,
与主机翼共同构成轨道器的双三角翼
comprising of the extensions themselves and the main wing.
Delta wing
简单来讲 三角翼就是三角形的机翼
To put it simply, a delta wing is a triangular shaped wing
名字来自希腊字母Δ(delta)
taken from the Greek capital letter Δ, which looks like a triangle.
三角翼能够产生升力
Part of how delta wings generate lift
部分是靠机翼前缘产生的涡流
is through generation of a vortex at the leading edge of the wing,
在机翼上表面产生近似抽吸的效应
creating sort of a suction effect on the upper surface.
三角翼后掠角度越大
The more extreme the angle of a delta wing,
产生稳定涡流的速度范围与攻角范围就越大
the wider range of speeds and angles of attack, where it can generate a reliable vortex.
因此 轨道器前缘根部延伸的作用就是让航天器能稳定提供升力
And so the Orbiters leading edge root extensions work to provide that capability of stable lift generation
并且让它有更宽的飞行包线
and a wider flight envelope than it would otherwise be capable of.
我们已经了解到控制阻力对于让轨道器维持在再入走廊中的重要性
We've now seen the importance of controlling drag to stay within the boundaries of the flight corridor,
也知道了如何让轨道器达到所需的阻力值
and how the Orbiter achieves this desire drag profile,
让我们能够安全地控制到达跑道的飞行距离
giving us the ability to safely control how much range we can fly to reach the runway.
接下来是再入制导中的另一个关键因素: 横向分量控制
There is now another crucial aspects to reentry guidance: cross range control.
我们要保证轨道器在向着跑道飞
We need to ensure that we actually fly towards the runway.
视角改为俯视图
For this, let's take a top down perspective.
绿色箭头是速度矢量 即当前飞行方向
The velocity vector shows our current direction of travel,
白色虚线是当前位置与跑道的连线
and this dotted line shows our displacement from the runway.
两者的夹角为航向偏差
The angle between these two is called azimuth error.
在制导系统中 航向偏差有一个可接受的范围 称为死区
And in the guidance system, there's an acceptable value of azimuth error, called Deadband.
还记得之前提到的 利用倾侧角控制阻力的方法吗?
Remember earlier when I was talking about bank angle and how we use it to control drag?
倾侧角一作用就是让轨道器的升力有一个水平分量
Well, a side effect of bank angle is that we're pointing some of the Orbiters lift sideways.
这个水平分量会让速度矢量向两侧移动 从而改变航向偏差
This will continually push the velocity vector to that side, affecting our azimuth error.
想要保持航向偏差在死区内
All we have to do to keep azimuth error within deadband
我们要做的就是在每次航向偏差达到死区边界时 翻转倾侧角方向
is to flip the direction of our bank angle, every time our azimuth error reaches the dead band.
翻转倾侧角方向的机动称为"倾侧角方向逆转"
Reversing the direction of the bank angle is a maneuver called a roll reversal.
我要阐明一点 倾侧角逆转的唯一目的就是控制航向偏差
And I want to be very clear that controlling azimuth error is the sole purpose of roll reversals,
并给轨道器容忍一定横向分量的能力
and it affords the Orbiter some cross range capability.
横向分量是指当前位置与跑道连线两侧的距离(红线)
Cross range is the distance capable of being flown to the side of a straight line path,
这样轨道器可以在最后与跑道对齐
allowing for corrected alignment with the landing side.
有时 侧倾角逆转会与"S形转弯"或"制动机动"混淆
Sometimes roll reversals are incorrectly referred to as an S-turn or a braking maneuver.
但S形转弯其实完全是另一回事 我稍后会提到
But S-turns are something entirely different that I will come too later.
而侧倾角逆转其实会带来制动的反效果
And roll reversals actually have an unintended opposite effect to braking.
逆转会带来阻力暂时的增加
They actually cause a temporary decrease in drag,
因为逆转方向时 倾侧角需要减小到零 再向反方向增加
because the bank angle has to be reduced and pass through zero degrees while reverse in the direction.
为了抵消这短暂的阻力减小 轨道器会在逆转时增加攻角
To offset this short drag decrease, the Orbiter will increase alpha modulation during the roll reversal,
并在逆转结束时 倾侧角会短暂超出一点 以增加阻力
and at the end of the roll reversal, perform a temporary over bank to increase drag.
现在 再入制导的大体内容已经介绍完了
We've now covered the general principles of reentry guidance.
我们接下来了解制导的几个具体阶段
Now let's step through the specific guidance phases.
首先是温度控制段
First is the constant heat rate phase.
此阶段中 阻力数值需要精确设计
During this phase, the drag profile is carefully designed
让进入绝热瓦的传导热通量
so that the conductive heat flux into the heat shield tiles
与流出绝热瓦的辐射热通量 达到平衡
is an equilibrium with the radiative heat flux out of the tiles,
保证在热量限制下温度状态的稳定
ensuring steady state temperature within thermal limits.
画面中为航天飞机隔热系统的绝热瓦
Let's look at a thermal protection system tile.
我们需要考虑的温度限制为外表面温度与内表面温度
The temperature limits we're concerned with are the front face temperature and the back face temperature.
如果该阶段阻力太大 外表面升温过快
If we're too aggressive with our drag during this phase, we'll heat the tiles too quickly,
超过了其本身热辐射的能力
outpacing their ability to radiate away heat,
外表面温度会超过其最大限度
and the maximum front faced temperature will be exceeded,
让绝热瓦失效 或造成损伤 影响复用
causing the tile to fail or become damaged, preventing reuse.
然而 如果阻力不够大 我们又会超过内表面的限制
However, if we're not aggressive enough, without drag, we'll exceed the back face limit.
听起来有点反直觉
And that does sound a little counterintuitive,
原因在于 即使是最小阻力下 绝热瓦也仍在快速升温中
but this is because even with minimal drag, we're still heating the tile a lot,
阻力变小 换来加热时间的延长
and by now extending this heating over a long period of time,
最终热量会传导到内表面
we're giving time for that heat to conduct through to the back face,
损伤轨道器的铝合金机身
where it can damage the Orbiter's aluminum airframe.
温度控制段时轨道器再入段中热量最高的时候
The constant heat rate phase was the highest heating region of the reentry,
TDRS: 跟踪与数据中继卫星
功能类似中国的天链 提供测控功能
在NASA的跟踪与数据中继卫星星座建成前
and before NASA's TDRS relay satellites were set up,
即黑障区
轨道器在该阶段会因机身周围高温等离子体的堆积而失去联系
this phase would incur a communications blackout due to the plasma buildup around the Orbiter.
下一阶段为虚拟平衡滑翔段
The next phase is the equilibrium glide phase.
该阶段始于速度低于约6.2km/s时
It kicks in after our velocity reaches below about 6.2 km/s.
虚拟平衡滑翔段作用相当于再入高热量与大气层内高阻力加速度的过渡
Equilibrium glide is sort of a buffer phase between the high heating portion of reentry
and the high deceleration portion, lower in the atmosphere.
该阶段内 轨道器可以有机会修正较大的再入航程误差
This phase is designed to give the Orbiter an opportunity to correct large ranging errors,
方法是增减飞行走廊内所需的阻力水平
and that can be accomplished
by commanding an increase or decrease in the desired drag levels within the flight corridor.
接下来是常值阻力加速度区 顾名思义
Next up is the constant drag phase, and its name is pretty self explanatory.
该阶段 轨道器的阻力加速度到达一个预定值
It kicks in when the drag deceleration of the Orbiter reaches a desired value,
通常为10m/s²
nominally 10 m/s²,
但为了修正再入航程误差 可以进行调整
but this can change in order to correct ranging errors.
该阶段 阻力加速度值会保持一个常值
Throughout this phase, the dragged deceleration value was well kept constant,
轨道器也会开始减小自身攻角
and the Orbiter would start the process of decreasing its angle of attack
准备进入更浓密的大气层中
as it starts to get into the thicker atmosphere.
此时攻角会从40度降低到33度
The angle of attack is lowered from 40 degrees to about 33 degrees.
接下来是再入制导的最后一个阶段
We are now onto the finals of reentry guidance.
过渡段
This is the transition phase.
该阶段 轨道器飞行方式开始像传统飞机那样
This phase transitions the Orbiter into flying much more like a conventional aeroplane.
攻角继续降低
The angle of attack continues to be decreased,
过渡到升阻比曲线中升阻比正相关于攻角的部分
transitioning to flying on the front side of the lift curve that I have mentioned earlier,
此时轨道器受到的阻力显著降低
and this significantly reduces the drag the Orbiter experiences.
以上就是再入制导段的四个子阶段
Those are the phases of reentry guidance.
接下来 一切都变了
And now for something completely different.
距离跑道90公里 高度24公里 速度750m/s时 再入段制导结束
At 90 km from the runway, at an altitude of 24 km, while traveling at 750 m/s, reentry guidance terminates.
"再入"过程结束 新的制导程序介入——末区能量管理(TAEM)
Reentry is now over, and we enter a new guidance regime called Terminal Area Energy Management.
在末区能量管理阶段 轨道器的飞行方式更接近传统的飞机
Under terminal area energy management, we're now flying much more like a conventional aeroplane,
制导系统也不再像再入段那样围绕"速度-阻力加速度状态空间"运行
and the guidance system is no longer operating in a velocity drag state space like it did during reentry.
而是围绕"能量"运行
Instead, it's thinking in terms of energy.
轨道器的能量 定义为其所在高度的重力势能 外加其速度所带的动能
The energy the Orbiter has is a combination of gravitational potential energy resulting from its altitude,
and kinetic energy resulting from its velocity.
末区能量管理段分三个子阶段
There are three phases in terminal area energy management:
捕获段 航向校准段 着陆前飞行段
acquisition phase, heading alignment phase and prefinal phase.
在末区能量管理段初始
At the start of terminal area energy management,
S形转弯也被称为末区能量管理的"阶段0"
如果轨道器能量仍有富裕 就该进行制动机动 即"S形转弯"了
if the Orbiter has excess energy, this is where it has the option to perform a braking S-turn maneuver.
如果不需要S形转弯 或者该机动已完成 轨道器(初始)能量正常
If an S-turn isn't necessary, or it's completed, and the Orbiter is at nominal energy,
就该进入捕获段了
the Orbiter will proceed through the acquisition phase.
画面中是着陆场的俯视图 来为大家介绍末区能量管理
This is a top down diagram of the landing site, showing the features of terminal area energy management.
有一条虚拟的跑道延长线 代表最终进近的航迹
There is an imaginary line extending from the runway center line, making the final approach path.
简称HAC: Heading Alignment Cone
与之相切的是四个"航向校准圆柱"
And placed tangentially to it are four HACs where a HAC stands for a heading alignment cone.
这些圆柱其实是单向盘旋下降的轨迹
These are single rotation spiral descent parts.
两个大的HAC位于通常切入点
The largest two HACs are placed at the nominal entry point,
两个小的HAC位于最小切入点
and the smallest two HACs are placed at the minimum entry point.
捕获段会制导航天飞机沿与其中一个HAC相切的路径上飞行
The acquisition phase flies the Orbiter on a tangent path to intersect one of the HACs.
切入HAC的目标点会标记为"航路点1"
The target HAC entry point is designated waypoint 1.
如画面所示 通常会标定跑道延长线另一侧的HAC
Nominally, the HAC position on the far side of the extended runway center line is targeted,
like you can see right now.
称为"飞跃机场进场"
This is called an overhead approach.
如果初始能量较低 或者有其他因素影响 如天气
In a low energy scenario, or in case of other influencing factors, like weather,
也可标定近侧的HAC 称为"直接进近"
the HAC on the near side can be targeted, creating what's called a straight-in approach.
如果初始能量非常低 还可以选择一个最小切入点的HAC
In a very low energy scenario, one of the minimum entry point HACs can be targeted.
HAC的直径可以在转弯时调整 保证正常的能量耗散
The diameter of a HAC can be modified during the turn to ensure a nominal energy dissipation,
还可以使用轨道器标志性的可劈叉的尾翼进行制动
as well as use of the Orbiters iconic split rudder speed brake.
离开HAC时
Upon exiting the HAC,
轨道器会对准跑道 建立着陆前飞行段的下滑道
the Orbiter is lined up with the runway and established on the glide slope in the prefinal phase.
随后 末区能量管理制导结束
And then terminal area energy management guidance ends,
轨道器进入进近与着陆制导
switching over to approach and landing guidance,
指令长会驾驶轨道器轻轻着陆
where the commander will fly the Orbiter through a smooth touchdown
并在跑道上全停
and eventually come to a full stop on the runway.
以上便是航天飞机的再入制导与控制介绍
That is Space Shuttle reentry, guidance and control.
本视频由我在Patreon上的赞助者赞助播出
This video was brought to you by my supporters on Patreon,
特别感谢最高档赞助的两位
with special credit going to the Highest tier: Martian Orbit patreons.
希望大家喜欢本期视频
I hope you enjoyed the video,
喜欢的话可以看看本频道的其他视频内容
and if you did, check out the Shuttle's payload bay for more simply space.